All right, data 5300 students,
module three, DDL, DML, and you've
done it. You've made it through
the vegetables of the course.
You've fought your way through
normalization. You've carved a path
through ER diagrams. And now,
we're going to put it all together.
We're going to use the ER
diagram that we've created,
and based on that, using nothing
but a blank sheet of paper, or in
our case, a SQL Server blank screen,
but for the exam, you know what
the question is. You'll be required
to code a DDL statement to create
tables. You'll also write DML
statements to insert tables, and we're
going to use that prototype example
that I mentioned where we have
student award and student. That's
what we're going to put together.
Let's go ahead and get
started. Let's do this.
Here's an example of what
we're going to create
today. This was a gift
given to me by my daughter,
Madison.
Create Table Best Dad Award. And
you can see we have recipient and
intelligence and humor and all these
great things, even some not nulls.
I did have to correct her.
This is technically the correct
version. Awful, isn't it? Awful.
But we did need some constraints,
and we'll talk about those
constraints in a minute. But
that's what we're going to do
today. We're going to go full
circle. We're going to start with
the DDL file. That's where we
create the database. We'll then
populate the database using DML,
using insert statements, and
then we'll drop the database, get
rid of it altogether, and then
just like the circle of life,
we've got the database here
where we can continue that
loop, create the tables,
populate the tables, drop the
tables, and go full circle.
Let's first do a normalization
check. And as I mentioned earlier in
the course, I like to use a prototype
example. So here is a student
table. We have student ID as the primary
key. We have the last name, first
name, and birth date. And in this
case, we have a gym locker, locker
ID, locker location. and then you
can see we have student last name
and this here is problematic if we
know the student id we would know
the student's last name we already
have it here so we can fix that by
improving our database from what
we have so we would do just a quick
normalization fix effectively
getting rid of student last name here
but now we have the link between
the two tables if this is a one-to
-one relationship we have the primary
key and the foreign key we place
the foreign key in the less
important table and that will be the
connection between the primary key
and the foreign key all right i do
have a separate video a short video
on how to log in to sql server
depending on the server that we're
using in a given semester this is
the most likely login that you'll
use We'll have the darksaber as our
server, darksaber.eggies.usu, and
then we'll do SQL authentication.
Your login will likely be, although
the video that shows you how
to log in or the instructions in
the syllabus would override this,
but 5300 underscore your first
name and last name as it appears
in Canvas, and then the password
is going to be database for your
particular account, unless if
you've changed it to something else.
So go ahead and get logged in if
you need to access the other video
to do so. That's fine. Just come
back to this particular spot.
And when you get logged in,
there are a couple of components
to SQL Server. And let me go
ahead and bring it on over
and show you some of the
elements that we'll be using.
The first thing is, and most
of you have worked in SQL in
some capacity, but if you haven't,
we have the execute button.
That's what we'll run when
we get the code ready to go.
Also, on the left side, we
have our object explorer.
I happen to be in a database called
OneCircle, and so you would find
your name, 5300 underscore first
and last name likely, but you can
expand that, and then you can expand
your tables, and that will show
you what table or tables you have
currently built. We'll also use
views and other programmability
later on in this class and then 5310.
But this is where you
can see your folders.
The other thing that you'll need
is this refresh button. SQL Server,
believe it or not, when you write
code, a lot of times if I create
a table and I run the code, it
doesn't show up until I refresh.
So if you can't find the table
and it looks like everything was
successful, you might just have to hit
the refresh button. Also, when I click
on New Query, I have something called
the Database Context, and right
now mine says, Master, yours you
don't have to change, and so during
the semester, if you see me type in
the word Use, and I'm going to go
down to that OneCircle database and
run this, and you'll see my Database
Context has now changed to
OneCircle. You won't have to do this
because this should be 5300 and then
underscore your first and last name.
If it's not showing up, then you'll
want to contact either the teaching
assistant or you can contact me
and we can help you through that.
All right, so here is
our blank sheet of paper.
We've already talked about data
types in the previous video,
but one of the things that
we will add to our DDL, our
create table, is we need to
indicate what data type we're
adding. So just as a reminder
for numeric data, we can add
integer, or we can add numeric
if we want some decimal places.
And again, these are
just two possibilities of
many that are available
to you in SQL Server.
We also have our character data,
where you could have a char 30,
which would give you 30 fixed
spaces for putting text in, or
a bar char, which takes more memory,
but then it gets rid of those
lagging spaces, so you wouldn't
have to use write trim. and
then we have a date-time function
written in years, month, day,
and then if you include
it, hours, minutes,
and seconds, and milliseconds, actually.
All right, so here's
what we're going to do.
If you would, go ahead and pause
the screen and type this out,
two dashes. We're going to
create our DDL, and that is our
create table, and this represents
the metadata for a database.
We have the DDL metadata, how
we create the tables and what
they look like, and then also
how to populate that database.
So to start out, we'll say
create table and the name
of our table. And in this
case, we'll call it student.
And then we start with, excuse
me, with our left paren, and
we're going to finish this
code somewhere, sometime with a
right paren and a semicolon. And
again, you can read in the Ben
Gaughan book, he talks about
why you would use a semicolon.
Similar to including a period
and a sentence, you just do.
But there are some coding
problems that we'll solve in data
5310 where you are required
certain common table expressions.
You are required to have the
semicolon or the code won't run.
Also, some of the older programs,
if you're using legacy systems, SQL,
they'll also require the semicolon
as well. So this is the basic
structure of a table. it still wouldn't
run I don't think yeah it still
wouldn't run we have to create at
least one column in order for that
to work and so in this case we'll
create some kind of id so student id
and on the exam you'll have to
create something it will be some kind
of theme so it could be a customer
it could be an employee it could
be a product it could be a pet
could be a any type of theme but the
but the structure would be the same
you'll create something that would
represent the primary key ideally
in this case we first give it the
name of the column or the attribute
and then we'll indicate what
the data type is and so we had that
selection of different data types
i'm going to just call this an
integer and then the next thing
we'll decide is if this is to be
null or not null meaning can you
leave it blank or not blank and of
course you know for a primary key
it has to be not null.
Now for student ID we're going to
create this as a surrogate key and
if you remember as a surrogate key
I mentioned if you had flashcards
you'd have probably three things.
You'd have the word identity along
with surrogate key and then with
identity you would have the starting
number and the increment number
and so for us we'll just write the
word identity and then for now we'll
just put one comma one and this just
means start at one and increment
by one and then we separate that
by a comma. Now this will become very
important when we start to insert
data and this is one of the things
people often miss on the exam is
they're trying to insert data and
they start to insert a student ID.
Well keep in mind the computer
system will automatically generate
that using our surrogate key so
when you're populating a data
set you ignore pretend that
surrogate key doesn't exist at all.
Then we can put in And then
just a couple of others,
just enough to demonstrate
we kind of know what
we're talking about. So
we have our last name.
And this could be a char or a varchar,
but I'll just call it a varchar30.
And then you can decide if
it could be null or not null.
I'm going to put not null and
then separate it by a comma.
And then my data might be a little bit
different, I guess, than
what we have over there.
I'm going to call this a varchar 30.
And then I think we
have this a birthdate.
And in this case we'll call it a date.
Probably date would be
fine but we'll call it
date or datetime if we
want to be specific.
And then in that case we'll
also leave this as not null.
And I'm going to put a comma
there. This comma allows us to move
on. And here's where we create
the primary key. And this could
be a multiple choice question on
the test. It could say student ID
is the primary key of this table.
And the answer to that right
now would be false. It's a surrogate
key. It's auto-generated. It
will likely be the primary key,
but it's not until we create the
primary key that it's made. And
there are also always a number
of ways to accomplish a task. This,
according to Ben Ghosn, is best
practice. So on the exam and
when you're working on labs, the
requirement is that you create a
primary key using a constraint,
and that's where we'll type this in here.
We'll have constraint, and now
the coding has to be exactly right
for the most part. What we'll first
do is we'll indicate what the name
of this particular primary key
is. And so to be consistent with
what we used in the example, I'm
going to call this student and then
underscore PK. I think that's what
I called it. So this is what we
refer to it as. That way later we
can alter it or drop it or make
changes. But this is the name of
it. So this could be whatever you
want to call it. Technically it should
be the name of the table underscore
PK so you clearly know this is
the primary key for this table.
And then the rest of it has to be
exactly typed exactly correctly.
It is primary key and then
we'll use a parentheses and
indicate what the primary key
of this particular table is, and
so we'll put in student ID,
and that creates a primary key.
I'll put a comma here. That comma
is optional at the very end, and
let's look at our slide. I think we
probably have it pretty close, and
if there's small differences,
that's fine, and so if you would
before you run this just take a you
know take a close look and make sure
you have your commas it's just
great when you run it for the first
time if it will actually run now
in this particular table we also
have foreign keys and you can see
here we we don't have a foreign key
because the table student is
the parent table so when we
create the gym locker table
we will have a foreign key.
All right, so I'm going to
go ahead and try it. Yikes.
Oh, good. Okay, so I think it
worked. So we've created four tables.
Let's take a look at
pushing the refresh button.
I'm going to open up
databases and one circle.
And there we have it. We have our
student table. Perfect. That's
the first part of the coding
question on the exam. Let's
take a look at the second part.
And this is where we have, again,
Ben Gaughan recommends this
style, so we'll use this style.
And the format, the approach
to it is insert and then the
word into. And my dear mother
passed away. It's been years
now, but we had a time on
the exam where a few people
just wrote the word insert and
then, for instance, student.
And so I took our little dog Texie,
RIP Texie, but I took Texie to class.
And after the exam, I put Texie
into the bag, into a bag, and she
loved it in class. It wasn't like
she loved it. and here's a picture
of Texie on the screen but anyways
it's insert into and so all the
years my mom lived she was able
to tell me how do you populate a
database insert into so insert into
and then we have the the student
which is the table and then
we indicate the columns that
we're going to add now if you see
what we have here we have last
name first name and birth date
and by birth date we're doing the
year the month and the day and
we have it as date time which is
fine. If we don't include a time,
it's always set, I think, to
midnight. But let's take a look here.
Remember, we have a student
ID column, but because it's
a surrogate key, we just don't
refer to it. So I'm going
to see if I can copy this. And
before I run this code, I'm
going to indicate select
everything from student table.
And when you're setting up the data
sets for the labs, you'll always
want to run the DDL first, and
what that will do is it will
create the structure of the database
tables, and then the next thing
you do is populate it. So this would
be the DDL, and this by definition
will be the DML, data manipulation
language. And when you run
just normal code, select star from
student, that's also considered
DML. Okay, so let's take a look.
I've got this code copied from
the slides. I'm gonna update the
slides just a little bit because,
or maybe I should leave them
just so you can troubleshoot.
But if I run this, we
get all sorts of stuff.
First one is we have an und
something something here.
And then the second thing is we have,
I guess it's, we have
this quote after 16 that
it doesn't like. So it's
a little bit confusing.
One of the things I need to do is
notice that parenthesis. again,
that is either a Word or maybe a
PowerPoint. If I try this, I'm still
getting an error message and I
think what's happening here is when
I copied the code over, it moved
this information to the next line
and so it's a little confused what
to do, I think, especially with
date times. Most of the time you
could go to the next line but it
should be the full the full word
like you wouldn't separate in insert
you would you bring the forward
there and I think that's what's
happening here so if you bring it all
back hopefully this will work perfect
so now we have one row affected
so you can indicate select star
from student fingers crossed and
there we go you've got you've
created the database. Now
you've populated the database.
Perfect. Now we can start the
not to one kind of thing. Sorry.
We have three options for
doing that. One is drop table,
and that's the one we'll do
for our circle of database.
But when you drop table and
the name of the table, poof,
it's gone. So you get rid of
it. The whole table's gone.
As a reminder, you do have to delete
the child table, drop the title
tables before you can drop the
parent table. So if we have a primary
foreign link, you first have to
drop the child table and then the
parent. So when you go under files
in Canvas, I've got the drop table
code for you for the university
data set or the antique data set
when there's more than one table just
so you don't have to keep reminding
yourself what are the child parent
tables. So you'll always have
three files in Canvas for your
data set. You'll have the DDL to
create, the DML to populate, and then
I'll have the drop table for you.
The truncate is if you want
to keep the table structure.
So when you remember, I ran it the
first time and we had this structure
without any rows. That's what
truncate, and then the name of the
table, and then student. And these
are all considered DDL, these two.
And then the third one is a really
dangerous one. We're going to
cover it next week in more detail.
But if you say delete from student,
you need a where clause, and
again we'll cover that next week,
you need a where clause. Without
it, it basically will get rid
of every row, and it's effectively
the same as truncating the
table. So I now have the create
table, I have the populate just
putting in one rows, and then I'm
gonna write drop table student.
We're at this stage right here,
drop the table, but then we'll get
into the loop. so now you know how
to drop the database table and if
I run this code expand it circle
table you can see that it's gone I
can now go over and run the code
to create it so now I refresh and
go back under circle and
tables and again if I run
this code it will only
have the column headings.
So now we've created it and then we can
populate it.
You can do this over and
over in an endless loop.
All right, I think we have
one more thing to cover.
Yes, I'm going to create
the gym locker table
and what I will do for
that is copy this code and
then I am going to describe
it on the other side.
and on the exam, you'll have to look
at the review sheet. So depending
on what we do in a given semester,
how much time we have, you'll
either just have to create the one
table with the primary key or you'll
have to create two tables with a
primary key and a foreign key link.
And that will be in the review
sheet. So you don't have to guess.
It will tell you one way or the
other for a particular exam. But the
setup is exactly the same. Create
table. We end with the parentheses.
The constraint for the primary key
is also the same constraint the
name of the locker we just called
it locker instead of gym locker
pk primary space key it's not case
sensitive and then locker id so
this is the primary key because we
created it here and then this is
the the technical writing for
creating a foreign key and it just
requires a little bit extra it
requires a reference statement For
instance, constraint studentLockerFK,
so this is just the name of it,
this is the name of the parent
table, the child table, this
is the foreign key, the foreign
key goes in the gym locker
table. We write the word foreign
space key just like we did
for the primary key, and then
student ID, which you can
see we have here, we had to
include here as our foreign key.
This takes care of the GymLocker
table, but now we have to
indicate what this reference
is. What's the parent table?
And so to create a
foreign key, you just have
one extra line of code
that says references,
the name of the table, references
the student table, and then
student ID. And so if we run
this, we've created a Jimlocker
table that is now referencing to
the student table in a primary
foreign key link. So as an example,
because of that, if I wrote
drop table and the name of the
table, in this case, student,
we'll see if that referential
integrity works. I'm trying to drop
the student table. I can't because
it's referenced in a foreign key
constraint, and therefore I would
need to drop table gym locker
first before I drop the student
table, and poof, now they're both
gone. that sums up what I'd like
to cover for today on the DDL and
DML you'll have plenty plenty
excuse me of practice opportunities
and I will see you next week where
we go over OLTP have a great day